Owen Lattimore Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Subject File, 1907-1979 (Box 22-26)
  - China
    - Historical material, notes and translations
      - Chou, Han, 1930-1937, undated, (4 folders)
      - Hsia, Shang-Yin, prehistoric, also indexes, etc., 1934-1937, undated, (2 folders)
      - Post Han, 1929-1936, undated, (2 folders)
    - Jehol, notes on trip to, 1933 (Box 25)
    - Printed matter
      - "Chinese Colonisation in Inner Mongolia," undated.
      - Horowitz, David, "China Scholars and U.S. Intelligence," undated
      - Newspaper clippings, undated
    - Research notes, undated, (2 folders)
  - China, Mongolia, and Russia, notes on, undated
  - Council on Foreign Relations
    - Study group on Far Eastern affairs, meeting minutes, 1946-1947
    - Territorial group, meeting minutes and reports, 1940-1943
  - Gobi expedition, 1979
  - Helsinki, Finland, notes on trip, undated
  - Inner Mongolia
    - Autonomous movement, undated
    - History notes, undated
  - Johnn, Gordon, "The Wagons Lits Buddhists: The Story of a Strange Pilgrimage," undated, (3 folders)
  - Manchuria
    - "Colonisation in Manchuria" notes, undated
    - Manchu vocabulary notebook, undated
  - Miscellany (Box 26)
    - Lists, undated
    - Research notebooks, undated, (2 folders)
  - Mongolia
    - Alphabet, 1958, undated
    - Mongolian studies, undated
    - Printed matter, 1961-1979, undated
    - Research notes, undated, (2 folders)
    - Translation of Mongolian dictionary, 1977-1979, undated
    - Vocabulary and articles on Mongolian tribes, undated
  - Outer Mongolia
    - Printed matter and newspaper clippings, 1961, undated
    - Research notes on conditions in 1911, undated
  - Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., 1929-1933, undated
  - Russia, research notes, undated
- Wartime Activities, 1934-1973 (Box 26-29)
  Correspondence, reports, summaries of conversations, biographical assessments, copies of diary pages, speeches, American and Chinese newspaper clippings, personnel records, and printed materials concerning Chiang Kai-shek, United States Office of War Information, and United States reparations mission to Japan, principally during and after World War II.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of person, topic, or type of material.
  - Air Transport Command special mission, 1944, (2 folders) (Box 26)
  - Biographical assessments and summaries of conversations, 1941-1942 (Box 27)
  - China
    - Air transportation, 1942, undated
    - Defense supplies, 1940-1942, undated, (2 folders)
    - Military mission, 1942
    - Newspaper clippings, 1941, undated, (4 folders)
    - Statements on the Pacific war by the Chinese Communist party and Chou En-Lai, undated
  - Correspondence
    - Chronological files
      - 1941-1942, (6 folders)
      - 1943-1952, undated, (3 folders) (Box 28)
    - Congratulatory letters, 1941, undated
    - Foreign language, undated
  - Diary, select pages from, 1945
  - Japanese, conversations with, 1937
  - Military Affairs Commission, undated
  - Miscellany, 1941-1973, undated
  - National Resources Commission, 1940-1941
  - Personnel records, 1941-1949, undated
  - Printed matter
    - Chiang May-ling Soong, "A Letter from Madame Chiang
      - Kai-shek to Boys and Girls across the Seas," 1940
    - "Efforts for Agreement with Japan," Foreign Relations, 1941
    - "Mongolia and the Peace Settlement," 1943
    - Newspaper clippings, magazine articles, and press releases, 1934-1945, undated See also Oversize, (3 folders)
  - Schuler, Frank A., Jr., resignation, 1944
  - Scrapbook, "U.S. Reparations Mission to Japan, November-December 1945" See Oversize
  - Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1942
  - Situation reports, 1941-1942, undated, (3 folders)
  - Speeches, broadcasts, and lectures, 1941-1946, undated (Box 29)
  - Wang Ch`ung-hui, 1936-1941, undated
  - Yarnell, Harry E., 1942
- Senate Hearings, 1910-1988 (Box 29-41)
  Correspondence with Lattimore's legal advisors, academic colleagues, and the public; published transcripts of hearings, Federal Bureau of Investigation reports, press releases, public statements, speeches, interviews, background files, newspaper clippings, brochures, and published articles, all pertaining to hearings held by the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, the Internal Security Subcommittee, and the Subcommittee Investigating the Institute of Pacific Relations; and briefs, summaries, motions, decisions, and other legal records relating to United States v. Lattimore and the lower and appellate court hearings.
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent, and thereunder by date in reverse chronological order; transcripts arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization, topic, or type of material; and briefs and legal records arranged chronologically by month and year and alphabetically by type of material therein.
  - Correspondence, 1941-1988, undated (Box 29)
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1950-1985, undated, (2 folders)
    - Barrett, Robert LeMoyne and Katharine Ellis, 1951-1963, undated
    - "B-D" miscellaneous, 1948-1985, undated, (7 folders)
    - "E" miscellaneous, 1951-1953, undated (Box 30)
    - Freedom Clubs, Los Angeles, Calif., 1952, undated
    - "F-J" miscellaneous, 1942-1960, undated, (8 folders)
    - Kizer, Benjamin H., 1951-1953
    - "K" miscellaneous, 1950-1978, undated
    - Little, Brown and Co., 1948-1949, undated
    - "L" miscellaneous, 1950-1955, undated, (2 folders)
    - "M" miscellaneous, 1950-1979, undated, (3 folders) (Box 31)
    - Newman, Robert P., 1978-1988, undated, (3 folders)
    - "N-R" miscellaneous, 1950-1984, undated, (5 folders)
    - Stefansson, Vilhjalmur and Evelyn Schwartz Baird
      - 1950-1954, undated
    - "S-T" miscellaneous, 1950-1976, undated, (4 folders) (Box 32)
    - Unidentified, 1941-1956, undated, (3 folders)
    - "U-Y" miscellaneous, 1949-1953, undated, (6 folders)
  - Congressional investigations, 1910-1987, undated (Box 33)
    - Exhibit materials
      - Excerpts of letters from people with knowledge of Lattimore's work, undated
      - Miscellany, 1940-1950, undated, (2 folders)
    - Fact sheets concerning Lattimore, undated
    - Fairbank, John King, public record of, circa 1972
    - Far Eastern Affairs Office, staff directory, undated
    - Federal Bureau of Investigation report on interviews of Lattimore, 1950, (2 folders)
    - Foreign Relations Committee
      - Statements before, 1950, (2 folders)
      - Warburg, James P., testimony of, 1963
    - Fortas, Abe, speeches by, 1953-1954
    - Grand jury, petition to unseal transcripts, 1987
    - Institute of Pacific Relations Subcommittee, transcripts of hearings
      - 25 July-7 Aug. 1951, (2 folders)
      - 9-23 Aug. 1951, (1 folder) (Box 34)
      - 26 Sept.-10 Oct. 1951, (2 folders)
      - 24-30 Jan. 1952, (2 folders)
      - 31 Jan.-2 Feb. 1952, (2 folders)
      - 29 Jan.-21 Feb. 1952, (2 folders)
      - 26 Feb.-3 Mar. 1952, (2 folders)
      - 4-21 Mar. 1952, (1 folder) (Box 35)
      - 10-27 Mar. 1952, (2 folders)
      - 28 Mar.-1 Apr. 1952, (2 folders)
      - 2 May-20 June 1952, (4 folders)
      - Judiciary Committee, report to, 1952, (2 folders)
    - Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md., Academic Council, undated
    - McCarran, Pat, statement of, 1952
    - McCarran Subcommittee, statement of Lattimore before, 1952
    - McCarthy, Joseph, misquotations in references to Lattimore's writings, undated
    - Miscellany (Box 36)
      - Names, lists of, undated
      - Notes, etc., 1950-1953, undated
    - Newman, Robert P., interviews with Lattimore, 1977
    - Notes on hearings, 1953
    - Owen Lattimore Defense Fund, contributors to, undated See Oversize
    - Press releases, 1950-1951
    - Printed matter
      - Boas, George and Harvey Wheeler, "Lattimore the Scholar," 1953
      - Congressional Record, 1950
      - DeMello, Duane, "The McCarthy Era: 1950-1954," 1968
      - Hart, Hornell, "McCarthy Versus the State Department," 1952
      - "Journeys Behind the News," 1951
      - Miscellany, 1944-1956, undated See also Oversize
      - Newman, Robert P.
        - "Bureaucrats as Heroes: Hoover's FBI in the Age of McCarthy," 1982, undated
        - "Lattimore and His Enemies," undated
        - "The Paranoid Style in American Rhetoric," undated
        - "The Self-inflicted Wound: The China White Paper of 1949," 1982, undated
        - Miscellaneous writings of, 1979-1985, undated (Box 37)
      - Newspaper clippings
        - 1950-1986, (10 folders)
        - Undated
        - Undated, (3 folders) (Box 38)
      - Vogelzang, Caroline, "The Vital Case: Senator Joseph R. McCarthy's Assault on Owen Lattimore," undated
    - Speeches of persons other than Lattimore, 1955, undated
    - State Department
      - Conference, 1949
      - General records of, decimal file, 1910-1929, and case no. 893.00, vol. 26
    - Statements made by Lattimore in his defense, 1952-1955, undated, (2 folders)
    - United States government records acquired by Freedom of Information Act requests
      - 1952-1986, undated, (5 folders)
      - 1938-1951, undated, (6 folders) (Box 39)
    - United States v. Laub, 1967
    - Utley, Freda, 1947-1952, undated, (2 folders)
  - United States v. Lattimore
    - 1952
      - Grand jury indictments, counts I-IV
    - Feb. 1953
      - Motion by defendant to dismiss the indictment and memorandum in support of motion
      - Motion for continuance
      - Motion for discovery and inspection before trial of documentary evidence
      - Motion for inspection of the minutes of the grand jury and a statement of authorities
      - Motion for leave to file motion for continuance
      - Motion for production of documentary evidence before trial and a statement of authorities
      - Motion for time to prepare and file motion for change of venue
      - Motion pursuant to rule 17 for production of documentary evidence before the trial
      - Motion under rule 7 for a bill of particulars
      - Preliminary statement reprinted from the memorandum in support of motion to dismiss the indictment (Box 40)
      - Statement of points and authorities in support of defendant's motion for inspection of documents
    - Mar. 1953
      - Defendant's reply memorandum
    - May 1953
      - Youngdahl, Luther W., opinion of
    - Oct. 1953
      - Brief for appellee
    - July 1954
      - Decision
    - Oct. 1954
      - Memoranda in opposition to the government's motion to strike
      - Motion for a bill of particulars
      - Motion to dismiss indictment
      - Motion to strike affidavit of bias and prejudice
      - Rover, Leo A., affidavit of
    - 1954
      - Grand jury indictments, counts I and II
    - Jan. 1955
      - Memorandum opinion
      - Supplemental memorandum in support of motion to dismiss
    - Feb. 1955
      - Cross-designation of record
    - Mar. 1955
      - Application to correct the record
    - Apr. 1955
      - Supplemental cross-designation of record
    - Undated
      - Appendix I to motion to dismiss the second indictment, (3 folders)
      - Brief and appendix for appellant
      - Brief for appellant and joint appendix
      - Brief of appellee
      - Insert in appellee's brief at page 42 (Box 41)
      - Offer of evidence
      - Points and authorities in opposition to motion to dismiss, (2 folders)
      - Reply brief for appellant
      - Reply brief of appellant
      - Supplemental memorandum of appellee
- Speeches and Writings, 1920-1987 (Box 41-54)
  Drafts or prints of journal, magazine, and newspaper articles authored by Lattimore, reviews of his writings, and some correspondence with publishers; transcriptions, notes, related correspondence, newspaper clippings, and published critiques on speeches, lectures, and films made by Lattimore; and drafts or prints of book reviews written by Lattimore for journals, magazines, and newspapers.
  Publications arranged alphabetically by title of article; speeches, lectures and films arranged chronologically; book reviews arranged alphabetically by name of author reviewed, or first author listed in case of works having joint and multiple authors
  - Publications and writings, 1920-1986, undated (Box 41)
    - Alphabetical listing of Lattimore's writings contained in his series
    - "A" miscellaneous, 1928-1950, undated
    - "The Border Life," 1926
    - "B" miscellaneous, 1928-1973, undated
    - "A Caravan Journey through Inner Mongolia," 1927
    - "China in History"
      - Chapters 1-6, undated, (4 folders)
      - Chapters 7-17, undated, (5 folders) (Box 42)
      - Lattimore, David, undated
    - "C" miscellaneous, 1928-1980, undated, (4 folders)
    - Diluv Khutagt (Box 43)
      - Autobiography, undated, (9 folders)
      - Bibliography, undated
      - Book reviews, 1983-1984, undated
      - Correspondence, 1975-1986, undated, (2 folders)
      - Interview transcriptions and notes, 1941, undated
      - "The Narobanchin Monastery in Outer Mongolia," 1952
      - Newspaper clippings, 1949-1963, undated
      - Notes, undated (Box 44)
      - Outline and introduction, undated
      - Photographs, 1938, undated
      - Political memoirs
        - Mongol manuscript, undated
        - Initial draft of translation, undated
        - Final draft of translation, undated
      - Research notes, 1949-1974, undated
      - Unidentified Mongol manuscript, undated
    - "D-E" miscellaneous, 1920-1978, undated, (2 folders)
    - "The Far East," 1946-1947, undated
    - "The Fate of Mongolia," undated
    - Fragmented, untitled, and unidentified manuscripts (Box 45)
      - China
        - Unidentified manuscript on, assorted pages from, undated
        - Unidentified manuscript on ancient history of, author unknown, undated, (2 folders)
        - Untitled manuscript on, pages from, undated
        - Untitled manuscript on pre-revolutionary period, author unknown, undated
        - Untitled paper on the development of post-World War II United States foreign policy with, undated
      - Frontiers, untitled and incomplete manuscript on, author unknown, undated
      - Inner Mongolia, untitled paper on "local nationalism" in post-revolutionary period, author unknown, undated
      - Mongolia
        - Manuscript on, undated
        - Untitled and incomplete manuscript on modern history of, undated
        - Untitled and incomplete paper on post-revolutionary period, author unknown, undated
        - Untitled and incomplete paper on the accomplishments of the Communist party in, undated
        - Untitled paper on the economic and industrial development of, undated
      - Stefansson, Vilhjalmur, memorial to, undated
      - Unidentified books
        - Chapters of, authors unknown, undated, (7 folders)
        - Introductions to, author unknown, undated, (3 folders)
        - List of contributors to, author unknown, undated
        - Preface to, author unknown, undated
      - Unidentified papers, fragments of, authors unknown, undated
      - Untitled manuscripts, authors unknown, undated, (2 folders) (Box 46)
    - "F-G" miscellaneous, 1933-1967, undated, (4 folders)
    - "Happiness Is Among Strangers," 1980, undated
    - "L'histoire et Ses Interpretations," 1961
    - "H-I" miscellaneous, 1928-1984, undated, (2 folders)
    - "J-L" miscellaneous, 1930-1973, undated, (3 folders) (Box 47)
    - "Mongolia," undated
    - "Mongolia in 1964," undated
    - "Mongols," undated
    - "M" miscellaneous, 1929-1987, undated, (3 folders)
    - "Nationalism and Marxism in the Mongolian People's Republic," undated
    - "Nomads and Commissars: Mongolia Revisited," 1960-1966, undated
    - "N-O" miscellaneous, 1928-1979, undated, (2 folders)
    - "P-R" miscellaneous, 1934-1980, undated, (2 folders) (Box 48)
    - Sambuu, Jamsrangiin
      - Animal husbandry in Mongolia manuscript, undated
        - Set A (edited draft)
        - Set B (annotated copy), (2 folders)
        - Set C (typed original), (2 folders)
      - Correspondence, 1972-1976
      - "From Serf to Sage: The Life and Work of Jamsrangiin Sambuu," 1976
      - "From Serfdom to Socialism: The Life and Work of J. Sambuu," undated
    - Silks, Spices and Empire: Asia Seen Through the Eyes of Its Discoverers, 1967-1970, undated
    - "Studies in Frontier History: Collected Papers (Box 49)
      - 1928-1958," 1963-1964
    - "Sung Yun's Journey," undated
    - "S-T" miscellaneous, 1928-1977, undated, (3 folders)
    - "West China Frontier Research Institute: A Manifesto in 1941," 1943
    - "Working for Chiang Kai-shek," undated, (3 folders)
    - "U-W" miscellaneous, 1933-1970, undated
  - Speeches, lectures, and films
    - 1928-1944
    - 1946-1971, (8 folders) (Box 50)
    - 1972-1987, (8 folders) (Box 51)
    - Undated
      - "China in History" lectures, (3 folders)
      - Miscellaneous lectures, (4 folders) (Box 52)
      - Transcriptions of lecture tapes, (7 folders); (1 folder) (Box 53)
  - Book reviews (arranged by author of book), 1933-1985, undated
    - A-V, (11 folders)
    - W-Z (Box 54)
    - Author unknown, 1964
    - Log of book reviews (incomplete), undated
- Miscellany, 1922-1991 (Box 54-59)
  Appointment books, biographical sketches, holograph journals with transcriptions, bibliographies, resumes, collection registers, newspaper clippings, passports, awards, degrees, printed matter, photographs, marriage certificate, wills and codicils, address books, and exhibit labels.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
  - Appointment books, 1964-1984, (4 folders) (Box 54)
  - Bibliography, 1962
  - Brochures, 1963, 1972
  - Exhibit labels, undated
  - French intelligence report claiming Lattimore to be a French spy, 1926
  - "Goyocephale Lattimorei," flat-headed pachycephalosaur from Mongolia, named for Lattimore, 1982
  - Honorary degrees and awards, 1930-1975, undated See also Oversize
  - Journals
    - Aug. 1922 (vol. 1)
    - Mar. 1926 (vol. 2)
    - Aug.-Oct. 1926 (vol. 3), (1 folder) (Box 55)
    - Oct.-Dec. 1926 (vol. 4), (2 folders)
    - Dec. 1926 (vol. 5)
    - Mar.-Aug. 1927 (vol. 6), (2 folders)
    - Sept. 1929-Sept. 1931 (vol. 7), (2 folders) (Box 56)
    - Dec. 1929-Apr. 1930 (vol. 8), (3 folders)
    - May-June 1930 (vol. 9), (3 folders)
    - Aug. 1932-Mar. 1933 (vol. 10)
    - [Aug. 1934?] (vol. 11), (3 folders) (Box 57)
    - May-June 1944 (vol. 12), (2 folders)
    - June-July 1944 ((vol. 13), (3 folders)
    - Undated (vol. 14)
    - circa 1961
    - July-Aug. 1964 (incomplete transcript)
    - Aug.-Sept. 1972
  - Lattimore, Eleanor Frances (sister), reviews of books written by, 1934, undated
  - Lattimore, Florence L. (sister), miscellaneous material, undated
  - Lidice, Czechoslovakia, regarding destruction by Nazis, 1947, undated
  - Marriage certificate, 1926 (Box 58)
  - Memorial volumes, 1972, 1980
  - Miscellany, 1960, undated
  - Names and addresses of correspondents, undated
  - Newspaper clippings, 1929-1984, undated
  - Notebook, undated
  - Owen Lattimore Collection at Brotherton Library, University of Leeds, Leeds, England, 1964
  - Passports and international certificates of vaccination, 1929-1984, (2 folders)
  - Photographs, 1966, undated
  - Subject index and notes to files, undated
  - Walter Hines Page School of International Relations, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md., register to the records of, 1923-1953
  - Wills, testaments, and codicils, 1970-1986, (1 folder) (Box 59)
  - World Youth Festival, 1947, undated
  - Writings on Lattimore
    - Aguiar, Mark, "Scholar and Scapegoat: An Intellectual Biography of Owen Lattimore, 1938-1952," 1988
    - Biographical sketches of Lattimore, 1950-1979, undated
    - "Owen Lattimore as a Historian of the Orient," Protiv Kolonializma, 1960
- Eleanor Holgate Lattimore Files, 1924-1970 (Box 59)
  Papers of Owen Lattimore's wife. Correspondence, book reviews, booklets, journal and magazine articles, newspaper clippings, employment records, obituaries, death certificate, and photographs.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Articles, 1924-1969, undated See also Oversize, (3 folders) (Box 59)
  - Book reviews, 1944-1948, undated
  - Correspondence
    - With parents, 1927, undated
    - With publishers, 1929-1944
  - Employment papers, 1947
  - Memorial booklet, 1970
  - Miscellany, 1933-1934, undated
  - Obituaries and death certificate, 1970
  - Reviews of Eleanor Lattimore's books, 1934-1947, undated
  - Society of Women Geographers, Bulletin, 1969
- Addition, 1970, 1997 (Box 59)
  A photocopy with ribbon and carbon ribbon pages of "Happiness Is Among Strangers." Although incomplete, this is a fuller version of Lattimore's autobiographical sketch than the original in Speeches and Writings.
  - "Happiness Is Among Strangers," with letter of Gary S. Dunbar, 1970, 1997, (2 folders) (Box 59)
- Oversize, 1931-1971 (Box OV 1-OV 3)
  Scrapbook of war reparations mission to Japan, magazine article on Chiang Kai-shek, posters, an award, honorary degree, two magazine articles authored by Eleanor Holgate Lattimore, and a list of contributors to the Owen Lattimore Defense Fund, on 3x5 cards.
  Arranged and described according to the series, boxes, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Wartime activities (Box OV 1)
    - Printed matter
      - Newspaper clippings, magazine articles, and press releases
        - "Chiang Kai-shek: The Leader of Fighting China Plays a Commanding Role in the Allied War Effort and the Destiny of All Asia," 1942 (Container 28)
    - Scrapbook, "U.S. Reparations Mission to Japan, November-December 1945" (Container 28)
  - Senate hearings
    - Congressional investigations
      - Printed matter
        - Miscellany
          - "ASSU Speakers Bureau and the Center for East Asian Studies Present 'Asia, America and the Legacy of Anticommunism, a Retrospective View of the McCarthy Era,'" circa 1971 (Container 36)
          - "Two Lectures by Owen Lattimore," circa 1971 (Container 36)
  - Miscellany
    - Honorary degrees and awards
      - Societas de Alexandro Csoma de Koros, 1971 (Container 54)
      - Academy of Sciences of the Mongolian People's Republic, Ulan-Bator, Mongolia, 1969 (Container 54)
  - Eleanor Holgate Lattimore files
    - Articles
      - "The Five High Passes of the Himalayas," 1942 (Container 59)
      - "Romantic Adventuring: Caravan Honeymoon," 1931 (Container 59)
  - Senate hearings (Box OV 2-3)
    - Owen Lattimore Defense Fund, contributors to, undated (Container 36)